Finding Aid for Schuler's Restaurant Records, 1944-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Schuler's Restaurant Records 1944-2002
Schuler's (Restaurant)
1 oversize folders
9 oversize volumes
18 linear feet (in 20 boxes)
05110 Bb 2; Bb Outsize
Historic restaurant based in Marshall, Michigan, specializing in American home-style cuisine. Since 1909, the Schuler family has owned and operated this Michigan institution. Records include administrative files, menus, advertising and publicity materials, slides, photographs, videotapes and scrapbooks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by Schuler’s Restaurant (donor no. 9609 ) in June 2005.
The record group is open to research.
The Schuler family restaurant business officially began when Albert Schuler, a local cigar maker, opened up his first cigar store in Marshall in 1909, adding a billiard table, bakery and a lunch counter. Delving further into the restaurant business, Albert purchased a café in 1917 and a hotel with a small dining room on Main Street in 1920. In 1924 he sold the Main Street hotel and purchased the more spacious Royal Hotel and Restaurant, the location where Schuler's restaurant continues to stand and operate today.
The history and growth of Schuler's can be attributed to the generations of the Schuler family who ran and managed this famous restaurant. In 1934, Albert gifted the restaurant to his sons, Winston ("Win") and Albert. Win and Albert remodeled and expanded the restaurant, adding a glass-block front and a bowling alley. While the bowling alley was later abandoned, it was converted into the "centennial room," a large dining area. In 1946, Win bought out his brother's share of the restaurant and continued to expand Schuler's, opening up several Schuler's restaurants throughout Michigan. In 1952, Win introduced Schuler's famous "Bar-Scheeze," a mixture of cheese and beer intended to sit at the table for diners to eat when arriving to their tables and waiting for their meals.
Win's son Hans took over the business in 1970 and was also lucrative in the expansion and renovation of Schuler's restaurant, contributing greatly to the mass marketing and growth of the Bar Scheeze product. In 1968, he trademarked and packaged the product for grocery store sales. In 1982, Hans helped sell the Bar Scheeze food division to Campbell's Soup.
As the fourth generation, Hans's oldest son, Larry continues the Schuler family restaurant legacy, Vice President of Schuler's Inc. and currently managing the casual "Schu's" restaurant in St. Joseph, Michigan.
From the 1950s to 1970s Schuler's expanded greatly, opening up restaurants throughout Michigan, with locations in Jackson (1952), St. Joseph (1954), Grand Rapids (1958?), Grand Haven (1963), Stevensville (1965), Ann Arbor (1972), East Lansing (1972), West Bloomfield (1974), Flint (1977), Rochester (1978), and Kalamazoo (1979) as well as Fort Wayne, Indiana (1970). Although the "Schu's" restaurant of St. Joseph (1990) remains the only subsidiary, the original Marshall restaurant continues to serve customers.
The records of Schuler's restaurant document the long history and background of this restaurant. The bulk of the materials come from the heyday of the restaurant from the 1950s to the 1980s when the restaurant experienced major growth and national recognition.
This record group contains the following series: Administrative, Advertising and Publicity, Menus, Visual Materials, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Schuler's (Restaurant); Restaurants--Michigan--Marshall.; Marshall (Mich.)--Commerce.; Cookery, American.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Schuler's (Restaurant); Restaurants--Michigan--Marshall.; Restaurants--Michigan.; Schuler, Hans.; Schuler, Win.; Schuler family.; Marshall (Mich.)--Restaurants.
Genre Terms:
Menus.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs); Videotapes.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (1 linear ft., 1969-2000) covers aspects of running and managing Schuler's restaurants, including public relations files, manuals and employee handbooks, and food and cost evaluations. The Administrative series also includes files covering special events planning, like the All-Michigan meal, Harvest dinners, and Michigan Week activities. Employee and family background materials can also be found here, including resumes and biographies of Win and Hans Schuler and the Board of Directors.
  - Awards and recognition (Box 1)
    (see also outsize folder)
  - Banquets (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors (Box 1)
  - Corporate Controls Systems (Box 1)
  - Cost evaluations (Box 1)
  - Food lists (?) (Box 1)
  - Handbooks and manuals (Box 1)
  - Hans Schuler biography (Box 1)
  - History (Box 1)
  - Newsletters (Box 1)
  - Public relations, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Special dinners
    - All Michigan Meal
      - 1986 (Box 1)
      - 1988 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Harvest Dinners
      - Advertising and planning (Box 1)
      - 1985 (Box 1)
      - 1986 (Box 1)
    - Michigan week (Box 1)
  - Win Schuler
    - General (Box 1)
    - Condolence letters 1993 (Box 1)
    - Quotes (Box 1)
- Advertising/Publicity
  The Advertising and Publicity series (1.5 linear ft., 1979-1986) contains scrapbooks of advertising and promotional clippings, loose files of coupons and promotions and Bar Scheeze advertising materials. The series also includes a clipping file of magazine and newspaper articles. See the scrapbooks series for more articles and publicity materials.
  - Advertising scrapbooks
    - 1975-1977 Jackson (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
  - Advertisements, promotions, etc., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Articles, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Bar Scheeze, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Postcards (Box 3)
  - Press releases (Box 3)
  - Promotion ideas (Box 3)
  - Skittles (Box 3)
- Menus
  The Menus series (7.5 linear ft., 1946-2002) includes various Schuler's menus including regular menus, changing menus, lunch and kid's menus, dessert and drink menus and special occasion menus. Of special note is the original menu artwork, demonstrating the planning, creativity and artistry that went into menu design at Schuler's. Menus have been arranged chronologically and by restaurant location. Undated menus have been organized by menu type.
  - Layout/design
    - General (Box 3)
    - Mini-menu design (Box 3)
    - Original menu artwork, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Skittles artwork (Box 3)
  - Menu and table items
    - Placemats (Box 3)
    - Table tents (Box 3)
  - Menus, by date
    - 1946 (Box 4)
    - 1950 (Box 4)
    - 1951 (Box 4)
    - 1952 (Box 4)
    - 1953 (Box 4)
    - 1955 (Box 4)
    - 1957 (Box 4)
    - 1958 (Box 4)
    - 1959 (Box 4)
    - 1960 (Box 4)
      (see also outsize box 19)
    - 1961 (Box 4)
    - 1962 (Box 4)
    - 1963 (Box 4)
    - 1964 (Box 4)
    - 1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968 (Box 4)
    - 1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1973 (Box 5)
    - 1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1976 (Box 5)
    - 1977 (Box 5)
    - 1978 (Box 5)
    - 1979, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1980, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1981 (Box 6)
    - 1982 (Box 6)
    - 1983 (Box 6)
    - 1986 (Box 6)
    - 1987 (Box 6)
    - 1988 (Box 6)
    - 1989 (Box 6)
    - 1992 (Box 6)
    - 1993 (Box 6)
    - 1995 (Box 6)
    - 2000 (Box 6)
    - 2002 (Box 6)
    - Outsize menus, 1 folders (Box 19)
  - Menus undated and other
    - Banquet menus (Box 6)
    - Breakfast menus (Box 6)
    - Children's menus (Box 6)
    - Dessert menus (Box 6)
    - Dinner menus (Box 6)
    - Drink and wine menus (Box 6)
    - Football menus (Box 6)
    - Harvest menus (Box 6)
    - Holiday/special menus (Box 6)
    - Lunch menus (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Pub menus (Box 6)
    - Specials, clip-ons, etc. (Box 6)
    - Outsize menus--undated, 1 folders (Box 19)
  - Menus, by location
    - Ann Arbor
      - 1974 (Box 7)
      - 1975 (Box 7)
      - 1977 (Box 7)
      - 1978 (Box 7)
      - 1979 (Box 7)
      - 1980 (Box 7)
      - 1981 (Box 7)
      - 1982 (Box 7)
    - East Lansing
      - 1977 (Box 7)
      - 1978 (Box 7)
      - 1979 (Box 7)
      - 1980 (Box 7)
      - 1981 (Box 7)
      - 1982 (Box 7)
      - 1983 (Box 7)
      - 1985 (Box 7)
      - 1986 (Box 7)
      - 1987 (Box 7)
    - Flint
      - 1977 (Box 7)
      - 1978 (Box 7)
      - 1979 (Box 7)
      - 1980 (Box 7)
      - 1981 (Box 7)
      - 1983 (Box 7)
      - 1984 (Box 7)
      - 1985 (Box 7)
    - Fort Wayne (Box 7)
    - Jackson
      - pub menu (Box 7)
      - 1977 (Box 7)
      - 1978 (Box 7)
      - 1979 (Box 7)
      - 1980 (Box 7)
      - 1981 (Box 7)
      - 1982 (Box 8)
      - 1982 Skittles (restaurant) (Box 8)
      - 1984 (Box 8)
      - 1985 (Box 8)
      - 1986 (Box 8)
      - 1987 (Box 8)
      - 1988 (Box 8)
      - 1989
        - lunch menus (Box 8)
        - dinner menus (Box 8)
        - holiday/special menus (Box 8)
        - wine menu (Box 8)
      - 1992 (Box 8)
    - Kalamazoo
      - 1979-1986, 8 folders (Box 8)
    - Marshall
      - 1977 (Box 8)
      - 1978 (Box 8)
      - 1979 (Box 8)
      - 1980 (Box 9)
      - 1981 (Box 9)
      - 1982 (Box 9)
      - 1983 (Box 9)
      - 1984 (Box 9)
      - 1985 (Box 9)
      - 1986 (Box 9)
      - 1986 wine lists (Box 9)
      - 1987 (Box 9)
      - 1987 wine lists (Box 9)
      - 1988 (Box 9)
      - 1988 wine lists (Box 9)
      - 1989
        - Lunch menus (Box 9)
        - Dinner menus (Box 9)
        - Dessert (Box 9)
        - Holiday/special menus (Box 9)
        - Wine menus (Box 9)
      - 1992 (Box 9)
      - 1993 (Box 9)
    - Rochester
      - 1977-1981, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - 1983 (Box 9)
        (in outsize box 19)
    - Stevensville
      - 1977 (Box 10)
      - 1978 (Box 10)
      - 1979 (Box 10)
      - 1980 (Box 10)
      - 1981 (Box 10)
      - 1982 (Box 10)
      - 1983 (Box 10)
      - 1984 (Box 10)
      - 1985 (Box 10)
      - 1986 (Box 10)
      - 1987 (Box 10)
      - 1988 (Box 10)
      - 1989
        - Lunch menus (Box 10)
        - Dinner menus (Box 10)
        - Holiday/special menus (Box 10)
    - West Bloomfield
      - 1977 (Box 10)
      - 1978-1982, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - 1983 (Box 10)
    - Outsize menus--by location, 1 folders (Box 19)
- Visual materials
  The Visual Materials series (6 linear ft., 1962-1999) contains slides, photographs, videos, and miscellaneous visual materials arranged by material type.
  - Slides
    Schuler's restaurant kept a photo file of their slides, arranged topically. This arrangement has been preserved, although there may be some overlap with the photographs. The topical slide files cover many different aspects of Schuler's restaurant including Schuler family, events and people, restaurants, food, bar scheeze marketing, and Schuler's memorabilia.
    - Awards (Box 11)
    - Banquets (Box 11)
    - Bar Cheese Marketing (Box 11)
    - Brunch (Box 11)
    - Centennial Room (Box 11)
    - Cheese Plant, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Cheese Plant Buildings and Trucks (Box 11)
    - Coloring Book (Box 11)
    - Dishline (Box 11)
    - Drinks (Box 11)
    - Food (Box 11)
    - Fort Wayne (Box 11)
    - Gift Certificates (Box 11)
    - Glasses (Box 11)
    - Golf Outing (Box 11)
    - Guests (Box 11)
    - Hans/Larry/Win (Box 11)
    - Holidays (Box 11)
    - Host/Hostess (Box 11)
    - Jackson (Box 11)
    - Kitchen (Box 11)
    - Lobby (Box 11)
    - Logos and Billboards (Box 11)
    - Memorabilia (Box 11)
    - Menus (Box 11)
    - Michigan week (Box 11)
    - Mug shots (Box 11)
    - News articles (Box 11)
    - Outside Schulers (Box 11)
    - Packaged Bar cheese (Box 11)
    - Promos, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Pub/Bar (Box 11)
    - Richland (Box 11)
    - Rochester (Box 11)
    - Training, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Wait staff (Box 11)
    - West Bloomfield (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 35 mm (Box 11)
      - 35 mm, 2 volumes (Box 12)
      - 2.75" x 2.75" (Box 12)
  - Photographs
    The photographs have been divided into four subseries: Activities and events, food, individuals, and restaurants. The activities and events photos document many of Schuler's anniversaries (70th, 75th, 80th, 85th, and 90th) as well as various awards banquets, parties and special meals. The food photographs include photographs of food prepared at the restaurant as well as bar scheeze marketing and preparation. The photographs of individuals document primarily members of the Schuler family, with the bulk of the photographs of Win and Hans, but also including some of Larry. Also included are employees, restaurant chefs, and Michigan governors, Blanchard and Milliken. The Restaurant photographs contain photos of the interior, exterior and renderings of the many Schuler's restaurants throughout Michigan.
    - Activities/Events
      - 4-H stock sales butcher shop (Box 13)
      - AAA "souper" bowl 1989 (Box 13)
      - Anniversaries
        - 70th (Box 13)
        - 75th, 2 folders (Box 13)
        - 80th (Box 13)
        - 85th (Box 13)
        - 90th, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Entertainment
        - General (Box 13)
        - Chamber music, Emily Byrens and Linda Jo Scott 1985 (Box 13)
        - Christmas carolers (Box 13)
      - Fly-in (?) July 21, 1996 (Box 13)
      - Golf
        - General (Box 13)
        - Bar Scheeze open 1977 (Box 13)
      - Michigan Harvest
        - 1985 (Box 13)
        - 1986 (Box 13)
        - Food (Box 13)
        - Governor Blanchard (Box 13)
      - Michigan week (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous events (Box 13)
      - Parties/Banquets
        - General (Box 13)
        - Awards dinner 1979 (Box 13)
        - Banquet 1987 (Box 13)
        - Inaugural banquet (Box 13)
        - Leukemia celebrity luncheon November 8, 1989 (Box 13)
        - Leukemia Society of America party undated (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous awards banquets (Box 13)
        - Parties (Box 13)
        - Taste of Detroit 1978 or 1979 (Box 13)
        - S.A.F.E. dinner 1989 (Box 13)
        - Travel Holiday awards
          - 1986 (Box 14)
          - 1988, 2 folders (Box 14)
          - 1989 (Box 14)
        - Win at banquets with employees, etc. (Box 14)
      - Sports (Box 14)
    - Food
      - General (Box 14)
      - Commissary (Box 14)
      - Bar scheeze/Bar schips (Box 14)
      - Food
        - 1990-1991 (Box 14)
        - 1992 (Box 14)
        - Food art (Box 14)
    - Individuals
      - Schuler family
        - General, 2 folders (Box 14)
        - Albert Schuler (Box 14)
        - Hans Schuler
          - General (Box 14)
          - 1985 (Box 14)
          - 1986 (Box 14)
          - 1987 (Box 14)
          - Governor Blanchard 1985 (Box 14)
          - Hans and Larry Schuler with wine 1987 (Box 14)
          - Hans and Dan Hugelier (Box 14)
          - Posed (Box 14)
          - Travel Holiday award photographs 1982 (Box 14)
          - With others, general and awards (Box 14)
        - Larry Schuler (Box 15)
        - Win Schuler
          - General, 2 folders (Box 15)
          - General photographs with people (Box 15)
          - Posed (Box 15)
          - Win and Hans Schuler with guests (Box 15)
      - Chefs
        - 1984 (Box 15)
        - Chef Dan Hugelier
          - 1984 (Box 15)
          - Detroit News (Box 15)
          - Olympics (Box 15)
        - Hans with chefs (and hunting) (Box 15)
        - Workshops (Box 15)
      - Other
        - Employees (Box 15)
        - Milliken (Box 15)
        - President Nixon at Marriott Inn (Box 15)
        - Unidentified and other individuals (Box 15)
    - Restaurants
      - Schuler history (Box 15)
      - Ann Arbor
        - General, 2 folders (Box 15)
        - Groundbreaking (Box 15)
      - East Lansing (Box 15)
      - Fort Wayne
        - General (Box 15)
        - Renderings (Box 15)
      - Grand Haven
        - Grand opening (Box 15)
        - Pre-1972 remodeling (Box 15)
      - Grand Rapids (Box 15)
      - Jackson
        - Black Jack Tavern (Box 15)
        - English newspapers (Box 15)
        - Exterior (Box 15)
        - Inn signs (Box 15)
        - Interior (Box 15)
        - Renderings (Box 15)
      - Kalamazoo
        - General (Box 15)
        - 1979 (Box 15)
      - Marshall
        - General (Box 16)
        - 1985 (Box 16)
        - 1986 (Box 16)
        - 1987 (Box 16)
        - Centennial Room 1988 (Box 16)
        - Gift shop (Box 16)
        - Heritage room (Box 16)
        - Hotel (interior) (Box 16)
        - Hotel Schuler (exterior) (Box 16)
        - Interior (Box 16)
        - Stadium rooms (Box 16)
      - Rochester (Box 16)
      - Stevensville
        - General (Box 16)
        - 1984-1987, 4 folders (Box 16)
        - Historic fire (Box 16)
      - St. Joseph
        - Construction (Box 16)
        - Exterior (Box 16)
        - Interior (pre-1972 remodeling) (Box 16)
        - Samuel Johnson (Box 16)
      - Troy
        - Renderings (Box 16)
      - West Bloomfield
        - General (Box 16)
        - Interior 1984 (Box 16)
      - Unidentified locations
        - Architectural pictures (Box 16)
        - Billboards (Box 16)
        - Historic buildings (Box 16)
        - Kitchen (Box 16)
        - Photos by Tines (Box 16)
        - Restaurant renderings (Box 16)
          (see also outsize Box 20)
        - Wait persons, uniforms, tables, kitchen staff (Box 16)
    - Other visual materials
      - Antiques (Box 16)
      - Art by Drausby (Box 16)
      - City of Marshall homes and buildings (Box 16)
      - Coaches and football games (Box 16)
      - Helicopter (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Videotapes (VHS)
    Videotapes: The videos include Schuler's 90th anniversary as well as a recording of a cooking show featuring a Schuler's recipe.
    - Schuler's restaurant 90th Anniversary 1999 (Box 16)
    - What's cooking with Burt Wolf? Schuler's roasted chicken (Box 16)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks (1944-1985, 2 linear ft., 9 oversize volumes) arranged chronologically, contain clippings, articles, menus, advertising and other memorabilia that Schuler's restaurant has compiled through the years. Also included is a scrapbook of Win Schuler.
  - Scrapbooks, by date
    - Win Schuler personal 1944 (Volume 1)
    - 1949-1973 (scattered) (Volume 2)
    - 1963-1975 (scattered) (Volume 3)
    - circa 1954-1974 (Volume 6)
    - 1960s (Volume 7)
    - Michigan Week 1962 (Box 17)
    - 1962-1966 (Box 18)
    - 1971-1976 (Volume 4)
    - 1972-1973 (Volume 5)
    - 1975-1978 (Volume 8)
    - 1977-1985 (Volume 9)
Additional Resources
Researchers may want to consult Schuler's: fresh recipes & warm memories, a cookbook put together by Hans Schuler and Chef Jonathan Schuler in 2004. In addition to featuring many of Schuler's recipes, the book also gives an excellent history of Schuler's restaurant, illustrated with historical photographs. The Bentley owns a copy of this book.
Schuler's restaurant also has a website (http://www.schulersrestaurant.com) that includes photo galleries, current menus, events, and a brief history of the restaurant.